<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="connector">
    <title>Firebase Simple Text Client</title>
    
    <section>   
      	<title>Overview</title>
		<para>
			The simple text client is a naive java client using text comments to communicate to 
			a Firebase server. It can be extended to handle non-Firebase commands.
		</para>
   </section>
      
    <section>
        <title>Using</title>
        
        <para>
            The simple text client can be used immediately to connect to a Firebase server. 
        </para>
        
        <section>
            <title>Connecting</title>
            
            <para>
                You connect to a server by simple starting the simple text client:
            </para>
            
            <para><programlisting><![CDATA[java [...].SimpleTextClient <host> <port>]]></programlisting></para>
            
            <para>
                The package name is removed above but should be "com.cubeia.firebase.clients.java.connector.text".
            </para>
            
            <section>
                <title>Encryption and Handshake</title>
            
                <para>
                    The simple text client support SSL, naive SSL (no certificate checking) and native Firebase 
                    encryption, as well as a protocol handshake. This is set via system properties
                    (which you can find in the <code>Constants</code> class). Please refer to the Java 
                    documentation for more information.
                </para>    
            </section>
        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>Commands</title>
            
            <para>
                Commands are given via the command line when the client is connected. Please type "help" to 
                get a list of all commands available.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    
    <section>
        <title>Extending the Client</title>
        
        <para>
            You can extend the simple client in order to handle you own commands.
        </para>
        
        <section>
            <title>Custom Commands</title>   
                   
	        <para>
	            You send command by extending the <code>handleCommand(String)</code> method. For example:
	        </para>
	        
	        <para>
	            <programlisting><![CDATA[[...]
	
@Override
public void handleCommand(String command) {
    /*
     * Do something here, first you may want to split
     * the command line into discreet comonents by whitespace,
     * or any other mechanism you prefer. For example:
     * 
     * String[] args = command.split(" ");
     * String cmd = args[0];
     * System.out.println("Command: " + command + " (" + cmd + ")");
     */
}
	            
[...]]]></programlisting>
	        </para>
        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>Custom Packets</title>
            
            <para>
                To handle incoming game packets from the server, extend the <code>AbstractClientPacketHandler</code>
                and override the <code>visit(GameTransportPacket)</code> method.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                <programlisting><![CDATA[[...]
    
public class MyHandler extends AbstractClientPacketHandler {

[...]
    
@Override
public void visit(GameTransportPacket pack) {
    /*
     * Do something here, the packet data will be in you
     * own format. For example, if the data is in UTF-8
     * string form, you could do like this:
     *
     * String s = new String(pack.gamedata, "UTF-8);
     */
}
                
[...]]]></programlisting>
            </para>
            
            <para>
                The simply add the new packet handler to the client by way of the <code>addPacketHandler(PacketVisitor)</code>
                method:
            </para>
            
            <para>
                <programlisting><![CDATA[[...]
    
SimpleTextClient client = // extended client
client.addPacketHandler(new MyHandler());

[...]]]></programlisting>
            </para>
        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>More Information</title>
            
            <para>
                Please refer to the community Wiki and message boards for more
                information about this component: <ulink url="http://www.cubeia.org">http://www.cubeia.org</ulink>
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>
